Finding Aid for Arthur H. Vandenberg Papers, 1884-1974
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Article of series July 9 - contrasts covenant & chart
(53b) - J. Alsop, "Stalin & Marshall" no date. Says AHV urged Marshall in Moscow, to be plain - speaking in Italian. Alsop says so far U.S. Foreign Policy has been bipartisan only in limited areas - U.N., peace treaties. In either field says bipartisan consultation only in emergencies. - AHV declined to make Greece-Turkey aid bill his own, for this reason. Felt he had no continuing responsibility in the area.
(53b) - Pearson Merry-Go-Round: relates AHV defense of Greece-Turkey bill before secret Republican Conference. Notes number of Republicans unhappy at idea of aid to Mid-East when Chiang slighted.
(54) - 3/18/47 - AHV critical of Democratic National Committee asking Republican opposition to get Democrats and Republicans jointly to endorse Greece-Turkey aid. Sees injection of partisan politics. Connally concurs. General remarks on bipartisanism.
(59) - Beverly Smith, "Russia's Pet Whipping Boy: Saturday Evening Post 4/6/47 - on balance, positive - notes value of being a convert; Austin & Willkie no such acclaim
- his love of words, florid speech, remark on "normalcy"
(60b ff) - On AHV amendments to Greece - Turkey aid bills
(61) - Lippmann - highly approves
(61b) J. Alsop: says AHV sprung it without consultation with Democrats in Senate or Exec. - J. Alsop says because AHV bothered by Marshall, Connally, & HST lack consultation; not take off, but crash land, etc. - notes no consultation re: China, South America.
(61 ff) - Lilienthal
(62b) - Reston on AHV Greece-Turkey amendments - how disarm those objecting - bypasses or weakens U.S.
(63) - Lilienthal fight: AHV widely considered to have beaten Taft
(83) - Cover of Time - May 12, 1947
(86) - European relief - Congressional Record
(90b) - Letter Acheson to AHV - May 29, 1947,upon DGA (Dean Acheson)
(91b) - HST letter, May 31, 1947, thanks re: Greece-Turkey
(94b-95) - Newspaper article by Krock (New York Times June 13 & W.S. White, on Marshall proposal - AHV proposes bipartisan advisory council to study, see how much U.S. resources can bear.
(99b) - June 22, dateline. HST appoints advisory group
-- The Tribune - publishes hostile remarks, even in it news stories, on AHV. Not to mention cartoons.
(109) - FDIC fight. Kept an independent agency, not under Bureau of the Budget [3] July 27 ff
(109 & 111 & ff) - Will go to Rio
(112b) - Marshall, July 30, 1947, thank-you letter for help on foreign relations during recent Congressional session
(116) - Bernard Baruch letter to AHV, July 30, 1947 - thanks
(116b) - HST Commission to AHV Rio, Aug. 4, 1947.
- following pages on Rio - hemisphere defense pact
(123) - New York Times Transcriptions [early Sept.], undated, of AHV's speech in Marshall - AHV radio report's on Rio conference
- AHV notes free discussion at conference
- no veto provision in treaty
- highly compliments colleagues
- defends treaty as consistent of U.N.
(128) - Both AHV & Mrs. in Butterworth Hospital, Grand Rapids; he "for a check up", she "recovering from an operation two weeks ago" (gallbladder)
(129) - Picture of AHV & Harriman, Sec. of Commerce
(129b) - Clark Clifford mentioned
(132b) New York Times dateline Nov. 3, AHV Ann Arbor speech
- calls for quick treaty with Reich
- separate treaty if Big 4 dead locks at London
(138b) - Time note (undated-late Oct. or Nov.) says China added to Marshall Plan at AHV behest; Marshall suppressed Wedemeyer's report
(139) - articles, one by Reston, dateline, Nov. 24 New York Times, on AHV speech for emergency aid to Europe -- France, Italy, & Austria (Reston's column in incomplete).
(140) - Newspaper text of Senate speech
(141) - Bill passes 83-6
(143) - Thank you note 12/5/47 from Marshall in London
(143b) - Senate approves Rio Treaty 72-1 - dateline Dec. 8
(144) - Tear sheets Congressional Record - text AHV speech for Rio Treaty, Dec. 8
(144b) - Morse says held campaign for AHV from coast to coast. "I consider him one of the giants of the Senate." Newspaper, no date on column
(145) - Congressional Record - remarks on indecision of China, at House request
(146b) - Krock ,dateline Dec. 15, "As the Republican Prospect Appears to Some" Reston, dateline Dec. 21. "V. wants a National Debate on Marshall Plan"
NO PERSONAL AHV TYPED NOTES ANYWHERE IN VOL. 19
Volume XX, 1948
(4) - New York Times dateline Jan. 5 - Felix Blair - AHV urges, Administration accepts, view that $17 billion figure specifically be withdrawn (this authorization is continuous). Do year-to-year.
(7) - Portrait in Parade, no date showing
(8) - Blair Moody, "Why V. won't Run" Washington dateline Jan. 5 Moody says Henry Wallace is right in saying AHV more than HST or Byrnes is responsible for "stand up to Russia"
(9) - Alsop & Alsop, "Virtue's Blackmail" no date - A very interesting analysis, in re: ERP, (European Recovery Program), of Marshall's & AHV's power coming from virtue of being "above politics". George Marshall for obvious reasons, AHV because withdrawal from Pres. consideration. Alsops say Marshall considers that rejection of ERP would be disastrous and that he won't preside over the consequences. Implications to Congressional leaders obvious. AHV has problems of maintaining (1)independence of the Administration and (2) leadership & standing in party. --Note he got specific figure of $17 billion removed the authorization remains. Notes AHV & Taft may oppose each other on this one, but notes difficulties of Taft's position within Congress.
(11b) - Ferdinand Kuhn, Jr. [Wash (?)] "Post Reporter" AHV critical on 4 points of ERP (1) lack of "business administration" (2) categorical statement U.S. aid depends on European cooperation (3) labeling of free goods sent to Europe (4) greater power for ERP administrator in Washington to recommend American ERP agents in each country--as it stands Sec. of State appoints in consultation with Administrator.
(11b) - Marquis Childs, no date, says AHV rightly saw the $17 billion figure as a stumbling block. Re: problem of administration overlap and policy control (Second Secretary of State) Childs applauds AHV's asking Brookings Institute to study whole problem and recommend
(23b) - New York Times dateline, Feb. 13, by Felix Belair on Senate Foreign Relations Committee approval ERP - for 12 rather than 15 months - sale of merchant ships prohibited
(25b) - Reston, New York Times, dateline, Feb. 15 on AHV backing Herter to be head of joint committee to watch ERP
(26) - Lippmann "The Marshall-Vandenberg Plan", no date "The administrative provisions are a decided improvement" [over original bill]
- 15 to 12 months, new goal; shows respect for 48 elections and new administration - also puts pressure on Europeans to get with it - as originally, provides $500 million a month.
(29) - letter 2/17/48 from Lewis Douglas, U.S. Ambassador to Great Britain. Thanks.
(30b) - letter-2/24/48 from Marshall -- "Personal" -- Thanks. Complimentary
(32) - Reston, Washington dateline 2/21/48 on AHV moves, changes to get ERP through
(34) - Congressional Record tear sheets ERP speech by AHV
(34b) - New York Times dateline 3/1/48, article on AHV speech
(39b) - clipping - Mrs. AHV not well enough to attend White House reception
(44) - Newsweek 3/15/48. AHV speech - 9000 words, 1 hr, 20 min according to Newsweek
(52) - Congressional Record tear sheets - aid to Greece and Turkey
(55b) - letter 4/1/48 from V.K. Wellington Koo, Chinese Embassy, with thanks, etc., from Chiang
(56) - Congressional Record tear sheets - w pages concerning aid to China
(57b) - AHV hollers & whistles from podium at Sen. Aiken won't stop speaking
(69) - Newspaper text, no date, of AHV speech before Michigan Chamber of Commerce
(73) - article Richard Rovere, "The Unassailable Vandenberg" Harpers Magazine, May, 1948
-- Much, almost verbatim, reappears in 1962 piece
(75b) - AP: "Pacts urged within U.N. on Defense"
(76) New York Times, Wk. S. White "V. backs Regional Aid within U.N. Charter"
- see card on these
(76b) -- "Vandenberg to back limiting Lilienthal Term" by Alexander H. Uhl. "Washington Bureau PM Exclusive" - author of note on whistle card labeled "China" & "Big"
(79) - Allen Hatch, "The Man who Doesn't want to be President" Liberty May 1948
(80) - J. Reston, "The Case for V" Life, May 24, 1948
(80b) Newspaper, May 19 dateline. Senate Foreign Relations Comm. unanimously passes AHV regional defense resolution.
(87b) - Krock says House has butchered Reciprocal Trade Act AHV has nobly risen in opposition to House action
(96) -- "Opinion: 'Strengthening the UN in Reverse,' PM, May 31, 1948 by Alexander H. Uhl. Critical of AHV resolution
(99) - June (?) 1948 newspaper article. Elmo Roper finds Eisenhower, as Democrat could beat any Republican, or as a Republican could beat any Democrat
(104) - Article by Bill Davidson. "The Two Mr. Vandenbergs". Colliers
(105b) - Wm. S. White New York Times dateline June 11, 1948 Senate 64-4 passes AHV resolution
(106) - Article by Tris Coffin, "Vandenberg and-the Great Temptation" - very positive; great description of AHV appearance, personality
(107) - Congressional Record tear sheets, 18 of them, on V. resolution
(109) - Art on Senate Appropriations Committee restore most ERP funds cut by House
(112) - June 15, New York Times dateline,-Wm. S. White. AHV feels his frontal assault on House Republicans over ERP funds precludes Pres. race by him. Couldn't ask to campaign for him.
(122) - Congressional Record tear sheets on Reciprocal Trade
(124b) - Newspaper article takes swipe at HST for remarks on "Western swing", criticism of congress
(129) - AHV typed note Philadelphia: June 20-25, 1948 - says no word with Taft at convention but Taft said few days before went he would want AHV as Secretary of State - felt "age & health rightly argued against my nomination"
(129b) - remarks on what a friendly press he has had
(130/130b-131) - Note: "The Platform"
- Lodge, Chairman of Resolution Committee, before Convention asked AHV for a working paper. AHV quotes it paragraph by paragraph and also right by puts platform paragraph. Almost verbatim. Lodge purposely added same extreme provision for isolationists to knock out. They were knocked out
(131) - Note: "The Vice Presidency" He urged Warren or Stassen, not a "hybrid" ticket in re: V.P.
(143) - Letter 6/27/48 from George E. Allen - who lost $100 bet to AHV.
Volume XXI, 1949 (book labeled 1948-1949)
(3) - Roscoe Drummond reports AHV is Ike's first choice for Pres. nomination
(2b) - Plans for trip to Europe canceled
(6b) - Marquis Childs says, AHV helped draft staff note just sent to Russia re: Berlin
(7) - Newspaper clipping, July 9, AP dateline. Reports AHV helped on note
(8b) - Alsops, no date, "Mr. Dulles Comes to Washington"
(9b) - several items here and FF on cloture ruling
(12) - Note on "acceptance" speech prepared for Republican Convention in case. - Says though some will think it evidence of lack of sincerity, just not so.
- notes parallels with Dewey speech. Not delivered of course.
(13 & 14b) - AHV's undelivered acceptance speech for 1948 National Convention
- his note on p. 12, he in fact justified it by saying newspapers all say at least 50% bet AHV get nomination
(15b) - AHV has given his copy of UN Charter to Clements Library
(19) - New York Times text of AHV Oct 4 (?) speech
(20) AHV typed note: "The Famous Truman-Vinson Incident, etc."
- says the idea got into the newspapers 3 days after it was dead White House had contacted radio chains for free time for HST to announce it; withdrew after Marshall in Paris elected; AHV thinks HST all along intended not to do it if Marshall elected
- Tues. Oct. 5 note: This was the morning HST talked with Marshall in Paris - that even-HST had AHV and Connally over for 1 hr. chat. No mention of Vinson Mission; AHV didn't know about it until later. Conversation seemed inconsequential though HST did say he might call Stalin by phone and see what could be done. AHV reacted to it as a casual conversation, didn't say yea or nay. - Sat. Oct. 9. Marshall home. HST 3 hr. talk with him and Soviet. AHV doubts wisdom of his going back to Paris with Marshall before UN decision; might seem we panicked, make them more intransigence.
- Fri. Oct. 22. Reston calls AHV in Grand Rapids re: rumor thru Krock that Pres. going to try another version of Vinson mission with AHV approval. AHV wired Press. secretary who relayed message to HST on train. AHV says his wire "pretty cryptic"
- Oct. 23rd. Message from HST via White House "Nothing will be done without consultation with you." AHV: "I thought that was very generous reassurance."
(22) - New York Times text of AHV Freedom House - Freedom Award speech. New York Times, Oct. 11.
(24b) - Jay G. Hayden "Vandenberg compromises with One Speech for Dewey", dateline Oct. 5. Subhead: "He stands firmly behind Gov. but doesn't want to anger Democrats."
(28) - Announcement AHV will get T. Roosevelt award
(31) - AHV typed note: "Secretary of State?" Fri. Nov. 5. There is something to the rumor that HST will make AHV Secretary of State. Biffle, HST friend, has recommended it. AHV talks with Biffle, especially wanting to prevent HST from making such an announcement without consulting AHV. AHV will listen if necessary to arguments for it, but, AHV feels independence he would want HST shouldn't let him have if Secretary of State, etc. Effect on Republicans
(32) - Robert T. Oliver article, "AHV" not dated or identified.
(32b) - Letter from HST, Nov. 6. Thanks for your congratulations.
(33) - Letter from Barkley. Thanks for congratulations.
(36b) - Newspaper article. "Senator's Daughter to be Piano Soloist"
(37b) - New York Times article dateline, Dec. 3 Rio Defense Pact... became effective
(38) - 12/10/48 note from Sec. Marshall
(39) - Newspaper, Dec. 3 dateline. Marshall has kidney ailment. AHV his choice for successor
(46) - AHV typed note. "The Incipient Republican Rebellion" - AHV discusses his attitudes, role in the challenges against Taft & Wherry.
(47) - Congressional Record tear sheets, AHV regrets Democrats make Senate Foreign Relations Committee one of the committees with 8-5 ratio instead of 7-6 for bipartisan emphasis
(47b) - Foreign Policy Comm. clippings
(48b) - First on Acheson appointment
(52b) - 1/7/49 letter from Robert A. Lovett. concerning resignation
(53) - 1/6/49 letter from Marshall - handwritten
(55b) - Acheson approved 83 to 6
(56) - 1/19/49 letter from Acheson
(56b) - New York Times, Jan. 21. AHV wary of "Pt 4" U.S. resources limited.
(58) - AHV typed note: Sat. Feb. 5, 1949. On China meet at White House. HST asks whether should cut off aid, etc. AHV counsels no. (Is in PPSV also)
(62b) - AHV Jr. groomed to succeed AHV Sr.
(65) - Appendix of Congressional Record, tearsheets. Lincoln Day Address.
(75B) - Wm. S. White story New York Times dateline 3/11/49 on AHV role in defeat of Barkley and cloture move. NAACP said AHV cost 5-7 votes. White refers to "his great political strength"
(78) - Newsweek 3/21/49 on cloture controversy
(82) - Text (New York Times) AHV speech on North Atlantic Treaty to the U.S. Conference of Mayors in D.C. c. 3/22/49.
(87) - 4/7/49 - letter from Bevin
(88B) - newspaper story - AHV Jr. takes post with "International Basic Economy Corp" - headed by Nelson Rockefeller. AHV, jr. Dartmouth grad.
(91) - AHV and Rayburn get Colliers distinguished Congressional Service award
(97) - Look Magazine - Washington correspondents rate senators
- Taft contributes most and most conscientious
- "AHV most popular and most statesmanlike"
- Pepper "best orator"
- etc.
(99) - Esther V.W. Tufty writes on AHV Jr. new post
(116) - 8/9/49 - letter, Hoffman to AHV (117) - Atlantic Treaty passes 82-13
(122B)- Newspaper piece mentions check-up and possible surgery
(127) - "Lung Lesion"
(127B) - 9/22/49 - Reston on cost to HST administration of "victory" on arms bill
(129B) - 9/15/49 - from H.R. Luce (letter) - says on recent trip in Europe saw remarkable recovery - AHV deserves much credit.
(130) - 9/19/49 - letter from Guillermo Sevilla Sacasa [Nicaragua] wants autographed picture
(131) - Final newspaper speech on arms bill - Congressional Record tear sheets
Volume XXII, Oct. 1949 - May 1950
(p. 1) -- AHV's lung operation
(2) -- 10/10/49 - letter from Adlai Stevenson
(3) - 2/6/50 -- "New Statement of Republican Principles" AHV typed note. (can find in PPSV)
(4B) - Telegrams from Churchill and Carlos P. Romulo
(10B) - Reston dateline 12/26/49 - mainly on AHV health and pains which are substantial
(11&12)-looks thinner and haggard in pictures
(11) - Newspaper story on press conference Good bit in article here about challenge within Republican party to bipartisanism in foreign policy. AHV's return to Washington in December not good for health, is seen in part as meant to prevent Republican attacks on and moves against foreign policy.
(13B) - Joseph C. Harsch, Christian Science Monitor -- "AHV fights for bipartisan foreign policy"
(14) - Marquis Childs, "V's Policy Fight"
(15) - Jay G. Hayden "Bipartisan Foreign Policy Is Put on Shelf by Truman"
(16) - Letter 1/11/50 from Senate Financial clerk acknowledging AHV refusal of mileage reimbursement.
(17) - Lippmann "Must General Bradley Testify?"
- a good case against summoning military chiefs for the purpose of getting information. Lippmann says can get it privately. Won't get it publicly, where whole world listens.
(18) - Reston 1/25/50 dateline - AHV quits JCAE Committee
(21) - Walter Trohan newspaper article - AHV wants son to succeed him.
(22) - 2/15/50 handwritten letter from David Lilienthal -- "Thanks ... last act at my desk as I leave..."
(23) - Handwritten note which accompanied book from Halifax
(24B) - Reston dateline 3/25/50. Letter to Hoffman made public.
(25) - 3/26/50 - Text AHV letter to Hoffman, New York Times.
(25B) - Reston, dateline 3/25/50. "V. Acts to Restore Bipartisan Policy" - mentions angry debates over Formosa and McCarthy charges - Bipart. really has been threatened. Taft, Wherry, others are encouraging McCarthy; Lodge, Stassen, etc., remaining quiet to avoid party fight; Acheson now a big point of contention. Reston says AHV's appeal for an unpartisan commission can point the way out.
(26) - New York Times dateline 3/26/50. "V. Plea for Post Aid Study Wins Wide Acclaim" - also editorial of New York Times on this page
(27B) - Empty envelope from White House. Letter missing.
(28) - Note: 3/28/50 - from Ike.
(28B) - W. Lippmann -- "The Isolationist Comeback" [in Republican Party]
(29) - Marquis Childs -- "Need for Republican Leadership"
(30) - Award letter from President of National Institute of Social Sciences 3/30/50.
(30B) - New York Times dateline 3/29/50 -- "Acheson Confers with V." - talk of appointing an Ambassador at large from Republicans to deal with Japan treaty. - talk of bipartisan commission, a la, pre-Marshall plan; suggested recent letters to Hoffman
(32B) - Alberto Lleras article "San Francisco Episode" (n.d.) on Article 51 of U.N. Charter. - brief newspaper notes on AHV's second operation
(33) - 4/13/50 - New York Herald Tribune editorial on operation
- "beautiful and poignant!"
- AP - Children are at bedside, Georgetown Hospital, of Mrs. AHV
(34B) - New York Times dateline 4/11/50 -- "V. Undergoes Operation; Tumor Near His Spine Is Removed" - at Georgetown Hospital -- doctors think this was reason for failure to recover satisfactorily from previous operation - preliminary tissue tests show tumor - non malignant
(35B) - Lippmann -- "To 'Recreate A Vandenberg'" - On Republican party splits. Says, can't have cooperation and consultation until policy proposal conceived somewhere. Don't have conceptions today.
(38B) - Martin Hayden dateline 5/20/50 -- "Vandenberg Votes Again: Senator Returns to Aid Filibuster Fight"
- first time back since February 3
- came to vote in favor of cloture - shutting off Southern filibuster on the FEPC bill.
- Mrs. V's condition "grave"